Josiah Bartlett Family Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Josiah Bartlett family papers 1710-1931 (bulk 1800-1890)
MSS11932
Bartlett, Josiah, 1729-1795
10,000 items
29 containers
11.6 linear feet
17 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Statesmen and physicians. Correspondence, diaries, diplomas, legal and financial records, notebooks, account books, speeches, genealogical material, printed matter, and newspaper clippings documenting the Bartlett family's professional and political activity in New England in the seventeenth, eighteenth, and nineteenth centuries. Topics include New England's sentiment towards the War of 1812 as well as American political life before and during the Civil War and post Civil War business developments.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Bartlett family.; Bartlett, Ezra, 1770-1848. Ezra Bartlett papers.; Bartlett, Josiah, 1729-1795.; Bartlett, Josiah, 1729-1795. Josiah Bartlett papers.; Bartlett, Josiah, 1768-1838. Josiah Bartlett papers.; Bartlett, Josiah, 1803-1853. Josiah Bartlett papers.; Bartlett, Levi, 1763-1828. Levi Bartlett papers.
Organizations
Republican Party (N.H.); United States. Navy.; Whig Party (N.H.)
Subjects
Depressions--1836-1837.; Indians of North America--Wars--1815-1875.; Medicine--Practice--New England.; Missouri compromise.; Seminole Indians--Wars.; Slavery--United States.
Places
New England--Commerce.; New England--Rural conditions.; New England--Social life and customs.; New Hampshire--Politics and government.; United States--Economic conditions--To 1865.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Hospitals.; United States--History--War of 1812.; United States--Politics and government.
Occupations
Delegates, U.S. Continental Congress--New Hampshire.; Governors--New Hampshire.; Judges.; Physicians.
Provenance
Although portions of the papers of the Josiah Bartlett family were acquired from multiple sources from 1938 to 1993, the bulk of the material was received by purchase in 1938 and by gift from Mrs. Mack W. Schwab in 1958. An addition was purchased in 1993.
Transfers
A map of the National Road from Washington, D.C., to Buffalo, N.Y., has been transferred to the Library's Geography and Map Division where it is identified as part of these papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of the Josiah Bartlett family are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of part of these papers is available on seventeen reels. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition as available.
Biographical Notes
Josiah Bartlett (1729-1795)
Date Event
1729, Nov. 21 Born, Amesbury, Mass.
1750 Moved to Kingston, N.H.; began to practice medicine
1750, circa Married Mary Barton
1775 1779 Member, Continental Congress
1776 Signed Declaration of Independence
1782 1788 Justice, Superior Court, New Hampshire
1788 Chairman, New Hampshire state convention to ratify the United States Constitution
1790 1792 President of New Hampshire
1791 First president, New Hampshire Medical Society
1793 Governor of New Hampshire
1795, May 19 Died, Kingston, N.H.
Levi Bartlett (1763-1828)
Date Event
1763 Born, Kingston, N.H.
1778 Attended Dummer School, Dummer, N.H.
1791 1819 Practiced medicine
1791 Joined New Hampshire Medical Society
1800 1806 Secretary, New Hampshire Medical Society
1804 Presidential elector
1816 1820 Judge of Circuit Court
1828 Died, Kingston, N.H.
Josiah Bartlett (1768-1838)
Date Event
1768, Aug. 29 Born, Kingston, N.H.
1789 Moved to Stratham, N.H.
1792 Married E. Wingate
1789 1829 Practiced medicine
1799 Member, New Hampshire Medical Society
1809 1810 State senator, New Hampshire
1811 1813 Member, United States Congress
1812 Married Hannah Weeks
1815 President, New Hampshire Medical Society
1816 1817 Treasurer, Rockingham County, N.H.
1824 President, New Hampshire state senate
1838, Apr. 16 Died, Stratham, N.H.
Ezra Bartlett (1770-1848)
Date Event
1770 Born, Kingston, N.H.
1794 Received medical certificate
1794 circa 1838 Practiced medicine
1798 Moved to Warren, N.H.
1799 Married Hannah Gale
1800 1823 Member, New Hampshire Medical Society
1806 State senator, New Hampshire
1812 Moved to Haverhill, N.H.
1816 Judge, circuit court
1820 Chief justice, Court of Sessions
1822 1824 Member, Governor's Council
1820 1828 Presidential elector
1848 Died, Haverhill, N.H.
Josiah Bartlett (1803-1853)
Date Event
1803, May 3 Born, Warren, N.H.
1812 Moved with family to Haverhill, N.H.
1824 M.D., Dartmouth College, Hanover, N.H. Moved to Stratham, N.H.
1824 1853 Practiced medicine, Stratham, N.H.
1824 1853 Member, New Hampshire Medical Society
1827 Married Hannah E. W. Thompson
1853 Died, Norwalk, Conn.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of the Bartlett family represent five generations of the family from 1710 to1931, with the bulk of the material concentrated between 1800 and 1890.
The papers consists of correspondence, diaries, notebooks, legal papers, diplomas, financial papers, account books, drafts of speeches, bills of lading, school compositions, genealogical material, photographs, maps, printed matter, biographies, obituaries, scattered individual issues of newspapers, and miscellaneous items.
The collection describes in detail the professional and political careers of Josiah Bartlett (1729-1795), signer of the Declaration of Independence and governor of New Hampshire, and his sons, Levi Bartlett (1763-1828) and Ezra Bartlett (1770-1848), both physicians and jurists, and Josiah Bartlett (1768-1838), physician, member of Congress, and president of the New Hampshire State Senate, as well as the papers of Ezra's son, Josiah Bartlett, (1803-1853), also a physician, and other descendants.
The papers primarily reflect the professional affairs of rural physicians and the daily activities and concerns of a large New England family in the seventeenth, eighteenth, and nineteenth centuries. Specific topics in the early correspondence include activities in Congress prior to the declaration of war on Great Britain in 1812, sentiment in New Hampshire favoring the war, and an account by an American combatant of the repelling of the British attack on Fort McHenry and Baltimore in 1814.
Later correspondence concerns the Missouri Compromise, Republican and Whig politics in New Hampshire, antislavery sentiment, the Seminole War, the Panic of 1837, life in the United States Navy, activities in military hospitals during the Civil War, and business developments in New England after the war.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in seven series:
Diaries and Notebooks, 1737-circa 1865
Correspondence, 1710-1931
Legal Papers, 1728-1913
Financial Papers, circa 1789-circa 1913
Speech File, circa 1800-1913
Miscellany, 1775-1931
Addition, 1783
Container List
- Diaries and Notebooks, 1737-circa 1865 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  Diaries and notebooks.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1737-circa 1865, (5 folders) (Box 1, Reel 1)
- Correspondence, 1710-1931 (Box 2-18, Reel 1-12)
  Letters sent and received.
  - 1710-1813, (5 folders) (Box 2, Reel 1-2)
  - 1814-1819, (6 folders) (Box 3, Reel 2)
  - 1820-1824, (6 folders) (Box 4, Reel 2-3)
  - 1825-1832, (6 folders) (Box 5, Reel 3)
  - 1833-1839, (7 folders) (Box 6, Reel 3-4)
  - 1840-1846, (6 folders) (Box 7, Reel 4-5)
  - 1847-1852, (6 folders) (Box 8, Reel 5)
  - 1853-1857, (5 folders) (Box 9, Reel 5-6)
  - 1858-1863, (6 folders) (Box 10, Reel 6-7)
  - 1864-1868, (6 folders) (Box 11, Reel 7)
  - 1869-1872, Apr., (5 folders) (Box 12, Reel 8)
  - 1872, May-1874, (5 folders) (Box 13, Reel 8-9)
  - 1875-1879, (6 folders) (Box 14, Reel 9)
  - 1880-1885, (6 folders) (Box 15, Reel 10)
  - 1886-1890, (6 folders) (Box 16, Reel 10)
  - 1891-1931, undated, (7 folders) (Box 17, Reel 11)
  - Undated and fragmentary, (6 folders) (Box 18, Reel 12)
- Legal Papers, 1728-1913 (Box 19-20, Reel 13)
  Indentures, deeds, contracts, court orders, depositions, case books, wills, and miscellaneous items.
  Arranged by type of material and chronologically therein.
  - Case books, 1825-1826 (Box 19, Reel 13)
  - Court orders, depositions, and warrants, 1789-1909, (3 folders)
  - Indentures, deeds, and contracts
    - 1728-1806
    - 1817-1902, (4 folders) (Box 20, Reel 13)
  - Wills, 1752-1913, undated
  - Miscellany, 1775-1903, undated
- Financial Papers, circa 1789-circa 1913 (Box 21-24, Reel 13-15)
  Bills and receipts, court payrolls, county receipts, and account books.
  - Account books (Box 21, Reel 13)
    - 1793-1802
    - 1789-1848, (2 folders) (Box 22, Reel 14)
  - Court and county accounts
    - County receipts, 1807-1817, (2 folders)
    - Court payrolls, 1812-1817, (2 folders)
  - Bills and receipts (Box 23, Reel 14-15)
    - Personal
      - circa 1795-circa 1819, undated, (5 folders)
      - circa 1794-circa 1913, undated, (5 folders) (Box 24, Reel 15-16)
    - Mills, George, circa 1817-circa 1848, undated
- Speech File, circa 1800-1913 (Box 25, Reel 16)
  Draft speeches by Josiah Bartlett (1768-1838), Josiah Bartlett (1803-1853), and Amos G. Draper.
  Arranged by type of material or author.
  - Speech drafts and notes (Box 25, Reel 16)
    - Bartlett, Josiah (1768-1838), circa 1800-1838, undated
    - Bartlett, Josiah (1803-1853), 1828-1850, undated
    - Draper, Amos G., 1860-1913, (3 folders)
- Miscellany, 1775-1931 (Box 26-29, Reel 16-17)
  Biographies, obituaries, genealogical material, printed matter, photographs, compositions, newspapers, newspaper clipppings, and pamphlets.
  Arranged by type of material.
  - Bills of lading, 1819 (Box 26, Reel 16)
  - Church papers, 1826-1837, undated
  - School compositions and notes, 1775-1875, undated
  - Diplomas and certificates, 1824
  - Insurance policies, 1825-1851
  - Legislative papers, 1781, 1814, undated
  - Maps, 1802, undated
  - Paper currency, 1800-1821
  - Petitions, 1791, 1810, undated
  - Photographs and prints, 1827
  - Miscellaneous official records, 1863-1930, undated
  - Biographies, eulogies, and genealogical material, 1801-1898
  - Miscellany, 1807-circa 1910, undated
  - Printed matter (Box 27, Reel 17)
    - Broadsides, proclamations, and circulars, 1804-1888, undated
    - Cards and tickets, 1811-1868, undated
    - Forms, circa 1790-1874, undated
    - Invitations, programs, catalogs, passes, and menus, 1821-1912, undated
    - Pamphlets, 1814-1819, undated
  - Newspapers (Box 28, Reel 17)
    - 1778-1877, June, (13 folders)
    - 1877, Aug.-1916, (7 folders) (Box 29, Reel 17)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1806-1931
- Addition, 1783 (Box 29)
  Letter from John Taylor Gilman to Josiah Bartlett (1729-1795).
  - Correspondence (Box 29)
    - Gilman, John Taylor, to Josiah Bartlett (1729-1795), 1783